<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on MMartinov</title>
    <link>https://martinov.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on MMartinov</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <managingEditor>me@mmartinov.com (Martin Martinov)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>me@mmartinov.com (Martin Martinov)</webMaster>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2016 14:44:47 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://martinov.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>El Chorro</title>
      <link>https://martinov.github.io/post/2016-02-el-chorro/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2016 14:44:47 +0200</pubDate>
      <author>me@mmartinov.com (Martin Martinov)</author>
      <guid>https://martinov.github.io/post/2016-02-el-chorro/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This morning I departed Malaga in magnificent weather - no clouds and temperatures around 23 degrees. With a group of London-based friends we&amp;rsquo;ve spent the last 5 days in El Chorro - a classic winter-sun destination, mostly visited by English and German climbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://martinov.github.io/images/2016-02-el-chorro/P2188670.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;El Chorro&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together with Jon we arrived in Malaga on Thursday, a day before the others. The plan was to have a look around, get familiar with the area and put some climbs in the bag. The weather wasn&amp;rsquo;t cooperating so we had to take it easy and be satisfied with the mystical views the rain and clouds had to offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the way to El Chorro we picked up a hitchhiker, a guy from Greece who was going to meet some friends and do the Caminito del Rei with them. He was living in Granada during the winter season to learn Spanish, as he&amp;rsquo;s working in the Greek tourism industry only during the summer. His dream was to sell ice cream on a little Greek island and told us he had just received the licence for that. We had a few beers at the bar next to El Chorro’s train station, and left somewhat unimpressed with the food they served us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We checked out some routes on the major crags around the village - &lt;a href=&#34;https://ukclimbing.com/logbook/crag.php?id=2488&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Frontales&lt;/a&gt;
 and &lt;a href=&#34;https://ukclimbing.com/logbook/crag.php?id=2485&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Las Encantadas&lt;/a&gt;
 and found the Olive Branch B&amp;amp;B. It looked quite good, prices were reasonable and it was full with like-minded people. We asked for places but it was pretty much full so we decided to stick with the initial plan which was to camp. For this purpose I had selected a VW Caddy from the rental car company, a vehicle with enough space for two people to have a comfortable night in. And it would have been pretty comfy if we had brought sleeping bags and mats with us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After having a great dinner in the Rocabella restaurant, we parked the car in the forest near Frontales and put most of our clothes on. We removed the back seats but couldn&amp;rsquo;t fit them in the front, so the bigger one remained stored in the back. It was a cold night and we had to start the engine at some point to warm up. I was even able to get some sleep, despite the few walks Jon had to make out in the rain. Unfortunately the next day wasn&amp;rsquo;t drier and again we couldn&amp;rsquo;t climb. We drove off to the upper dam and had a look further along the road, where the entrance for Caminito del Rei is supposed to be. Then we went back to Malaga, to pick up Romina and Marti, who arrived after lunch. Together we went grocery shopping, then wandered around El Chorro and went to pick up the keys for the villa which Zhivko had booked. The other part of the crew arrived late in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://martinov.github.io/images/2016-02-el-chorro/P2198741.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;Caminito del Rei&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of us gathered for breakfast and a short discussion on where to climb that day followed. Marti suggested a new sector, not included in the guidebooks yet - Cucina Caliente, just above the Olive Branch, and we decided to give it a go. It was a good option for our group - everyone had something interesting to do - there are 11 routes there, from 5 to 6b+. I was satisfied at the end of the day because I&amp;rsquo;ve managed to do all of them onsight. We had a great day out and a nice evening in the villa, where Romina cooked a delicious paella.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://martinov.github.io/images/2016-02-el-chorro/P2208756.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;Romina leading one of the routes at Cucina Caliente&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the next day we woke up early with Romi and went to do a nice long route in the middle of Frontales - Lluvia de asteroides (6a, 250m). I led all the 8 pitches, nice climbing on mostly solid rock, felt a bit easy for the grade. We reached the top for 6 hours, including a lunch break after the 4th pitch, which was a point of commitment for us, as we only had a single 70m rope, and that pitch was 39 meters long. But we didn&amp;rsquo;t had any issues to the top, where we easily found the rappel anchors for the way back. We had some problems finding the way to get down but eventually, after following some goat paths, walking down a dry river canyon, crossing a train bridge and climbing a fence we found ourselves at the lower car park. I was proud with Romina&amp;rsquo;s performance this day as this was her first multipitch route ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third (and last) day of climbing was not that fruitful, but also nice. The highlight for me was a route called Putiferio, a real 3 star pitch, 30 meters, hard for the grade. I&amp;rsquo;ve also tried a 6a and 6b+ but couldn&amp;rsquo;t do them clean because we had to take Romi to the airport. I guess I was a bit tired from the previous two days. We should have rested that day but there was nothing to test for as we were flying away on the next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We woke up this morning and had an awesome breakfast outside on the terrace. Then Jon went for a shower and we left for the airport. At this point we&amp;rsquo;ve realised it&amp;rsquo;s a bit late, so I had an excuse to do 180 km/h on the highway. We&amp;rsquo;ve managed to get to the airport on time and I ran off to find my gate. Jon was flying later so he got the responsibility to return the car.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I am, halfway through the flight to London, contemplating on the El Chorro experience. It was a good one for sure, but there were some glitches too. If it wasn&amp;rsquo;t for the nice winter climate around Malaga, I&amp;rsquo;d say Vratsa is a better climbing destination. Similar amounts of rock, a lot of potential for new routes in both places, but not so crowded and no sign of electrical companies and constant humming of cables in the air in Vratsata.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking forward to the Mallorca trip in March, but before that we&amp;rsquo;ll do a short one to Greece.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Climb On!</title>
      <link>https://martinov.github.io/post/2015-07-summer-climbs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2015 18:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>me@mmartinov.com (Martin Martinov)</author>
      <guid>https://martinov.github.io/post/2015-07-summer-climbs/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bmc-icm-2015-north-wales:02bded238d106164e9d45df9646f2bcf&#34;&gt;BMC ICM 2015 - North Wales&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got back to the rocks shortly after the previous post. In fact, on the very next day. Together with Rado we went to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.climbers-club.co.uk/venues/ynyws/&#34;&gt;Climbers&amp;rsquo; Club Hut Ynys Ettws&lt;/a&gt; in the heart of Llanberis Pass, North Wales to participate in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thebmc.co.uk/bmc-international-summer-climbing-meet-2015&#34;&gt;BMC International Summer Climbing Meet&lt;/a&gt; from 10-th to 17-th May.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;thumbnail pull-right&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a data-flickr-embed=&#34;true&#34;  href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/mmartinov/17194163594&#34; title=&#34;P5156553&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5469/17194163594_a3d1b8afbc_n.jpg&#34; width=&#34;320&#34; height=&#34;240&#34; alt=&#34;P5156553&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src=&#34;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34; style=&#34;width:300px;&#34;&gt;
    Phillip Thomas on the approach to Cyrn Las where we did a true classic - Main Wall.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was an amazing experience and although a bit difficult for me at times because of my back, I had a great time and I&amp;rsquo;m glad that I did it. With my spine still recovering from the fractures, I had to climb very carefully (almost like free solo, as someone put it). I&amp;rsquo;ve decided that I won&amp;rsquo;t allow myself any falls or highly dynamic moves, so I had to stick to the lower grades when leading. This gave me an opportunity to do some really beautiful, classic routes which were totally worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve met awesome people at the event and made some friends - in total there were participants from more than 30 different countries. Together with my hosts we were at a different crag every day, like Tramadog, Tryfan in the Ogwen Valley, Gogarth and others. In the next weeks and months I kept bumping into people from the meet wherever I go climbing for the weekend. A &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/mmartinov/sets/72157652624400499&#34;&gt;photo album from the meet&lt;/a&gt; is available on flickr.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;thumbnail pull-left&#34; style=&#34;margin-right: 10px;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a data-flickr-embed=&#34;true&#34;  href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/mmartinov/18130440175&#34; title=&#34;P5246647&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8858/18130440175_b70b40fff1_n.jpg&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; height=&#34;320&#34; alt=&#34;P5246647&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src=&#34;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34; style=&#34;width:220px;&#34;&gt;
    My friends on the start ledge.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;end-of-may-north-wales-again:02bded238d106164e9d45df9646f2bcf&#34;&gt;End of May - North Wales again!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I fell in love with North Wales climbing, so the next weekend we went there again, this time with a group of friends - the regular Bulgarian crew (Rado, Milena, Marti, Deni, Lucho, Stanke) + Jon and &lt;a href=&#34;https://skinpoetryphotography.wordpress.com&#34;&gt;Shay&lt;/a&gt;. We had some rain on Saturday and did mostly hiking and scrambling, also some practice on placing gear in the cracks of the slab next to the camping. The day ended with some easy solo ascents on that piece of rock. On the next day we went to Castell Helen at Gogarth where we had a perfect day of relaxed climbing. Some &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/mmartinov/sets/72157651165806214&#34;&gt;photos from that trip&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;llanberis-trad-fest:02bded238d106164e9d45df9646f2bcf&#34;&gt;Llanberis Trad Fest&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t remember why I had to skip the next weekend, but the one after - you&amp;rsquo;ve guessed it, North Wales again. This time it was the &lt;a href=&#34;http://dmmclimbing.com/news/2015/04/llanberis-tradfest-2015/&#34;&gt;Trad Fest&lt;/a&gt; - &amp;ldquo;a celebration of north Wales’ trad climbing heritage; stretching from the mountain crags of Llanberis and Ogwen to the dramatic sea-cliffs of Gogarth and the Lleyn.&amp;rdquo;
I went together with Jon and we&amp;rsquo;ve managed to do two multi-pitch routes, one each day. It was his first time following up on multi-pitch, having to clean and then on the way down I&amp;rsquo;ve also showed him how to abseil, it was a good experience and I think he enjoyed it. On Saturday evening &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.leohoulding.com/&#34;&gt;Leo Houlding&lt;/a&gt; gave the best presentation I&amp;rsquo;ve ever seen to date. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/mmartinov/sets/72157653818650008&#34;&gt;Photo album in flickr&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cornwall-climbing-fest-h4:02bded238d106164e9d45df9646f2bcf&#34;&gt;Cornwall Climbing Fest&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;thumbnail pull-right&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a data-flickr-embed=&#34;true&#34;  href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/mmartinov/19296820831&#34; title=&#34;P6286752&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3858/19296820831_d587509bac_n.jpg&#34; width=&#34;320&#34; height=&#34;240&#34; alt=&#34;P6286752&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src=&#34;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34; style=&#34;width:300px;&#34;&gt;Zheny and Deni playing on the edge.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next thing was the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thebmc.co.uk/www.thebmc.co.uk/bmc-cornish-climbing-walking-festival-2015-bosigran-cornwall&#34;&gt;BMC Cornish Climbing &amp;amp; Walking Festival&lt;/a&gt; at the Climbers’ Club hut, The Count House. No one from my friends who have cars were able to come, so I had to give rent-a-car a go. It worked almost flawlessly. Driving in London on a Monday morning isn&amp;rsquo;t that fun, so I was late for work the day after the trip, but otherwise it was all fine. I went to the fest with Zheyna, Deni and Emi and managed to take them up on two good routes at Bosigran on Saturday. The fest itself was a blast, very good food, even better talks and a friendly bunch of people (both local and from all over the country). I&amp;rsquo;ve met some friends from the ICM here too. Everyone was genuinely interested in the &amp;ldquo;Bulgarian group&amp;rdquo; and I had some funny conversations and useful advice from local climbers on what to do the next day. Unfortunately the weather wasn&amp;rsquo;t that good, so we went for a walk and ended up in a local pub with fantastic Sunday roast. In the beginning of the trip I&amp;rsquo;ve told my friends that I can handle two girls, but I&amp;rsquo;m not sure about three. Everything was cool and smooth so maybe next time I should probably try four? &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/mmartinov/sets/72157652931929444&#34;&gt;Photos from the trip&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;thumbnail pull-left&#34; style=&#34;margin-right: 10px;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a data-flickr-embed=&#34;true&#34;  href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/mmartinov/19728355411&#34; title=&#34;P7106912&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/408/19728355411_97b752b34e_n.jpg&#34; width=&#34;320&#34; height=&#34;240&#34; alt=&#34;P7106912&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src=&#34;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34; style=&#34;width:300px;&#34;&gt;A friend from the locals bidding us farewell.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;back-home:02bded238d106164e9d45df9646f2bcf&#34;&gt;Back home&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this month I had the opportunity to fly over to Bulgaria and work remotely for a week. I&amp;rsquo;ve got the Friday off and went straight to my favourite mountain, Rila. Together with one of my best friends Dani we&amp;rsquo;ve decided to try a route we&amp;rsquo;ve been dreaming about for a long time. The name is Chayka (Seagull) - a classic alpine route, 500 meters long, the grade doesn&amp;rsquo;t go above 6a if your route finding is good enough. The weather was trying to scare us with fog, a distant thunderstorm and a few drizzles pissing on us but we kept going. It took us 9 hours to complete the climb. At one point (after pitch 6) I&amp;rsquo;ve took a wrong way up and ended up on a massive run-out (15 meters?), but miraculously managed to find a creative small nut placement somewhere amongst the lichen and went up for another run-out. Eventually I&amp;rsquo;ve found a peg and we were back on route. We enjoyed the climb greatly and I&amp;rsquo;m looking forward to do other long climbs with Dani. We didn&amp;rsquo;t get many good views because of the fog but nevertheless - the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/mmartinov/sets/72157655510518218&#34;&gt;photos are great&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;relaxed-trip-to-sunny-devon:02bded238d106164e9d45df9646f2bcf&#34;&gt;Relaxed trip to sunny Devon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;thumbnail pull-right&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a data-flickr-embed=&#34;true&#34;  href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/mmartinov/19827270506&#34; title=&#34;P7197014&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/517/19827270506_f41b700994_n.jpg&#34; width=&#34;320&#34; height=&#34;240&#34; alt=&#34;P7197014&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src=&#34;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34; style=&#34;width:300px;&#34;&gt;Blackchurch rock.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last weekend we went to Devon with a bunch of people. After a mishap on Saturday morning (we&amp;rsquo;ve got lost with the car), in the afternoon we&amp;rsquo;ve finally found the Lower Sharpnose Point and we&amp;rsquo;ve abseiled down together with Deni and Jon to do route. Unfortunately by that time the tide was going up and we didn&amp;rsquo;t had much choice and I ended up quickly leading an unpopular VS route (some loose rock) so that my friends didn&amp;rsquo;t get wet. The Smile and the Lunakhod routes remain on my list, both of them look amazing, and the whole crag seems very interesting and extraordinary.
On Sunday we went to Blackchurch, had a look at the cliffs around and some people went for a swim, the rest of us climbed up the Blackchurch rock. Most of the people wanted to get back to London rather early so we didn&amp;rsquo;t climb something more interesting - again, another interesting place worth a trip on it&amp;rsquo;s own. Looking forward to go there again this summer.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/mmartinov/sets/72157655701279910&#34;&gt;A set of photos can be found here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between the climbing weekends there were a few water-related - a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/mmartinov/sets/72157654852339400&#34;&gt;boat trip to Newbury&lt;/a&gt;, swimming in a lake near &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/mmartinov/sets/72157655508145245&#34;&gt;Rye House&lt;/a&gt; and a short visit to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/mmartinov/sets/72157655853981146&#34;&gt;beach in Greece&lt;/a&gt; with my family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all - a great summer so far, despite the major injury in the beginning, together with great friends I&amp;rsquo;ve managed to do some awesome things. That&amp;rsquo;s what life is all about, isn&amp;rsquo;t it?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An update from the doctor</title>
      <link>https://martinov.github.io/post/2015-05-09-update-from-doc/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2015 21:20:35 +0100</pubDate>
      <author>me@mmartinov.com (Martin Martinov)</author>
      <guid>https://martinov.github.io/post/2015-05-09-update-from-doc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday was the last day to wear the brace. Actually I got it off on Thursday evening, but anyway.. Freedom!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Friday morning I had a review with the doctor who did the operation. They&amp;rsquo;ve made new X-rays and were very happy and positive. He said the fractures haven&amp;rsquo;t moved at all and everything looks great!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can&amp;rsquo;t wait to get back to the rocks.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How I broke my back</title>
      <link>https://martinov.github.io/post/2015-04-19-how-i-broke-my-back/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2015 19:07:16 +0100</pubDate>
      <author>me@mmartinov.com (Martin Martinov)</author>
      <guid>https://martinov.github.io/post/2015-04-19-how-i-broke-my-back/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s been two weeks since I got out of the hospital. I’ve spent a night in the emergency and a week and a half in the Major Trauma unit. I’ll have to wear a TLSO brace for another three weeks. I shouldn’t be complaining because that’s the minimum, before the operation the doctors were saying it could be 10 or more weeks until my back is stable enough to go unsupported. Everything went well with the operation and according to the doctor, my recovery is also going excellent for now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember everything from the night of the accident. We were climbing at the Westway. That’s the indoor climbing wall I’m visiting after work every other day. I was with my regular climbing partner Rado, his girlfriend Milena, his nephew Toni and some other people, one of them a guy whom I’ll call Flamen.
Milena and Toni are relatively new to climbing, just taking their first steps in leading so together with Rado they&amp;rsquo;ve dedicated the evening to practice falling. He was belaying and showing them different techniques. While they were resting, he was climbing with me, we were trying some challenging routes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point Rado went to see how his people are doing. It was half past nine and we had another half an hour to call it a day. I’ve decided to do some easy routes in that remaining time. Have you heard that most climbing accidents happen in the end of the day, or on the way down from a climb? Flamen was up for belaying me, so we started. I’ve climbed up an easy 6a and then down-climbed it, to start immediately another one. When I got down, I pulled the rope, had a look at Flamen to see if he had put the rope correctly through his belay device and started the next one. I did this a few times. I was getting tired but that was the idea, to carry on as long as I can. And then it happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was two clips away from the top, something like 30 ft (10m) from the ground. I saw the next move is going to be hard for me in my current state, had a quick look down and saw I’ve got some slack and my belayer is talking to somebody. Instead of shouting “watch me”, or grabbing an easier hold from another route, or a quickdraw, or something else, I tried to do the move. I&amp;rsquo;ve spent a lot of time in the past to train my brain to be able to give everything I have to the route I&amp;rsquo;m climbing. I was probably subconsciously hoping that although my belayer is not paying attention, he’ll catch my fall because he was using a Trango Cinch (an assisted-braking belay device, similar to Petzl Grigri). &amp;ldquo;I might pull him off a bit but he’ll catch me.&amp;rdquo; Wrong! I don’t remember the actual flight after I got off the wall. I lost consciousness when I hit the ground. When I got back from this strange land of mixed rainbow lights and sounds, there was a small group of people around me. My friends, two other regular climbers and a member of the staff. They&amp;rsquo;ve later told me I wasn&amp;rsquo;t there for about 40 seconds. I was laying on the floor and someone was holding my head and telling me to not move. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t feeling any pain, I remember slowly understanding what had happened and telling them everything is OK and that I&amp;rsquo;m fine. Somebody had already called for an ambulance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They&amp;rsquo;ve untied me from the rope and also removed the belay device from the other end. People later told me that the guy from the staff has inspected everything and it was all set up correctly. Nobody had any idea about what exactly had happened. My belayer didn&amp;rsquo;t knew I was falling until I&amp;rsquo;ve hit the ground next to him. He didn&amp;rsquo;t had any burns or other traces from the rope on his hands so everyone thought he wasn&amp;rsquo;t holding the dead end when I fell. He was probably holding the Cinch incorrectly, that’s the most commonly expressed assumption. I guess it&amp;rsquo;s a combination of that and the fact that he&amp;rsquo;s not very experienced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve met Flamen three or four months ago at the wall. He was a coming with another guy, they were beginners but visiting regularly and our group is always friendly to strangers, especially when they&amp;rsquo;re from the same nationality. So we started belaying each other in the gaps when we didn&amp;rsquo;t had our regular partner around. I&amp;rsquo;ve had a few falls on hard routes and Flamen didn&amp;rsquo;t had any problems catching them. Unfortunately I wasn&amp;rsquo;t able to learn anything from him about the accident. Two days after it happened he visited me in the hospital but wasn&amp;rsquo;t able to say anything meaningful or answer any of my questions. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t harsh with him or anything, I only wanted to understand a bit more about what had happened. I haven’t heard from him since then. This speaks a lot about the type of person he is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, we have a saying in Bulgaria that bad things don&amp;rsquo;t go alone. Something else happened shortly after this. It was emotionally much more painful than breaking some bones. It&amp;rsquo;s about a girl I was in love with and I&amp;rsquo;ll keep it off of the internet. Why I&amp;rsquo;m mentioning it then? Because my point is - when an accident like this happens to you, you&amp;rsquo;re forced to learn. For example, you learn to only put your life in the hands of people you truly trust. But more importantly, you learn a lot about the people around you. It&amp;rsquo;s sad that some people choose the easy way out, but that&amp;rsquo;s their own problem after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, my friends, my family, my colleagues were with me all the time, supporting me from the first day in the hospital. They were helping me by any means they could think of. It is a great thing to know that there are people who actually care and it&amp;rsquo;s inevitable to feel that everything will be all right in the end if you&amp;rsquo;re surrounded by such a group of colourful and awesome personalities. I am humbled and deeply thankful to each one of them for the responsiveness and sympathy they are giving me every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a lucky escape! During the surgery they&amp;rsquo;ve put &lt;a href=&#34;https://martinov.github.io/images/x-ray/image1.jpg&#34;&gt;two rods and 6 screws&lt;/a&gt; in my &lt;a href=&#34;https://martinov.github.io/images/x-ray/image2.jpg&#34;&gt;vertebrae&lt;/a&gt;, and they didn&amp;rsquo;t touch the lower fracture, which later turned out to be a good decision, as the doctor observed it&amp;rsquo;s healing properly on it&amp;rsquo;s own. Hopefully I&amp;rsquo;ll be fully recovered soon. But there are people who die because of belayer errors. Don&amp;rsquo;t trust everyone, just because they&amp;rsquo;ve got a harness and can put a rope through the belay device properly. Be safe and take care of your partners!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.climbing.com/skill/essential-skills-be-a-better-belayer/&#34;&gt;skills needed to be a better belayer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also have a look at the funny video below to see how NOT to belay:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/V9hsWjA3SmU&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First attempts at rock climbing</title>
      <link>https://martinov.github.io/post/2015-03-16-climbing-first-attempts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2015 22:03:14 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>me@mmartinov.com (Martin Martinov)</author>
      <guid>https://martinov.github.io/post/2015-03-16-climbing-first-attempts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Every now and then when I meet new people, they&amp;rsquo;re asking me how and when did I started climbing. I usually tell them - it was the summer of 2010, when I took it seriously. The full story is a bit longer. I don&amp;rsquo;t actually remember the year of my first climbing attempts, it was probably around 2001. What I do know is that I was in high-school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my friends had a brother who gave us a rope, 4-5 quickdraws, a normal climbing harness and another one, made up from sewn together seat belts from &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/VAZ-2103&#34;&gt;Lada&lt;/a&gt;. We knew some routes existed on rocks near the town so we went there and figured it out this way: whoever is climbing takes the good harness and the quickdraws, goes up until there are no more quickdraws and then climbs down. The belayer gets the belt-harness and the figure of eight belay device, then we swap roles. We didn&amp;rsquo;t knew anything about abseiling and free climbing back then, just two teenagers trying out something new.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We didn&amp;rsquo;t managed to kill ourselves which was good. Also, we both liked climbing. Life went on and we didn&amp;rsquo;t had a chance to continue our adventures - we had to study for exams and similar stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a couple of years, now in university, I tried again. There were sport classes we could choose from and climbing was on the list. Unfortunately it was indoors, and always on toprope, so I didn&amp;rsquo;t liked it very much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the items in my new year`s resolutions for 2008 reads:
&lt;div class=&#34;well&#34;&gt;
  &amp;ldquo;Try skydiving again or at least bungee jumping or something.. just to feel the pull from the other side. Maybe some rock climbing would be good too, haven&amp;rsquo;t done it for more than 3 years. Also more hiking this year &amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;
&lt;/div&gt;
Well, I haven&amp;rsquo;t been doing skydiving recently but I&amp;rsquo;ve bungee jumped from a hot air balloon, which counts. Anyway, back to climbing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;thumbnail pull-right&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a data-flickr-embed=&#34;true&#34;  href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/mmartinov/4829728489&#34; title=&#34;dsc_0819&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://c2.staticflickr.com/5/4122/4829728489_3c6fd0708d_n.jpg&#34; width=&#34;320&#34; height=&#34;213&#34; alt=&#34;dsc_0819&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src=&#34;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34; style=&#34;width:300px;&#34;&gt;
    This is how it all started for me - from the cradle of Bulgarian alpinism - Malyovitsa.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another few years passed by and my girlfriend told me that some colleagues from her group are going to a gym for climbing, maybe we could try? So we did, and this time I was fascinated. After a few sessions I&amp;rsquo;ve subscribed for a week long climbing course in the mountain. My idea was not only to refresh my knowledge but mainly to meet people who are serious about outdoor climbing. This was in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/mmartinov/sets/72157624460097339/&#34;&gt;July 2010&lt;/a&gt; and I consider it the date when I started climbing properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, after some time, that girl who kind of re-introduced me to climbing broke up with me (we&amp;rsquo;re still friends), because she thought I was more interested in climbing than anything else, including her. Which, in retrospect, was probably partially true.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>