<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pages on MMartinov</title>
    <link>https://mmartinov.com/page/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pages on MMartinov</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 May 2016 19:52:11 +0300</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://mmartinov.com/page/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello, my name is Martin</title>
      <link>https://mmartinov.com/page/work/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2016 19:52:11 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mmartinov.com/page/work/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was born in &lt;a href=&#34;http://pleven.bg/en/&#34;&gt;Pleven&lt;/a&gt;, a town in the central north region of my beautiful country - &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bulgaria&#34;&gt;Bulgaria&lt;/a&gt;. After finishing school I moved to the capital - Sofia and lived there for a decade. I&amp;rsquo;ve spend my time building a career and extensive experience in few web development companies, but mainly Propeople (now &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.drupal.org/ffw&#34;&gt;FFW&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What followed were a couple of years when I did some consulting work for foreign companies in Copenhagen, Hamburg and Vienna, including the International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA). This led to a decision to try living abroad and seeing what would it be to work full-time in another country. I choose the UK when I joined &lt;a href=&#34;https://ndp-studio.com&#34;&gt;NDP&lt;/a&gt; as a senior Drupal developer in late December 2013. I loved London and working with the team, but after two years there I felt it was time for something different. We&amp;rsquo;ve made a deal with the management for me to work remotely. This way I was free to come back to Bulgaria and continue working for the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently I&amp;rsquo;m living and working in Sofia, for one of the biggest fintech companies in Bulgaria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a programmer and open source software enthusiast. I stared writing code when I was 11 and tried installing Linux for the first time few years later. Initialy my professional expertise was with LAMP stacks (Linux/Apache/mySQL/PHP) but lately I&amp;rsquo;ve been more interested in the JavaScript world (Node.js, React, Vue.js). I am capable of administering a variety of Linux distributions, &lt;a href=&#34;https://debian.org&#34;&gt;Debian&lt;/a&gt; being my choice most of the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My primary skills are as a &lt;a href=&#34;https://php.net&#34;&gt;PHP&lt;/a&gt; developer and I possess considerable knowledge of JavaScript, HTML and database design &amp;amp; management. I&amp;rsquo;ve been working with PHP &amp;amp; mySQL since 2003 (15+ years of commercial experience). In that time I&amp;rsquo;ve been responsible for the development of 4 different custom CRM systems and countless web sites and applications. For some of these I&amp;rsquo;ve used frameworks like CodeIgniter, Symfony and Express, and for others I&amp;rsquo;ve build my own code base from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve dedicated 10 years of my career to focusing mainly on &lt;a href=&#34;https://drupal.org&#34;&gt;Drupal&lt;/a&gt; projects. Traditionally my role has been developing custom modules, extending contributed modules and helping the team by solving challenging technical problems. Most of my latest work on Drupal projects consists of writing custom modules communicating with different 3rd party systems via SOAP or REST APIs and migrating data from various legacy databases. I have also contributed some modules (&lt;a href=&#34;https://drupal.org/project/webform_term_opts&#34;&gt;webform_term_opts&lt;/a&gt; as an example) and patches to other modules. My &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.drupal.org/u/mmartinov&#34;&gt;Drupal.org profile&lt;/a&gt; has more related information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lately, I&amp;rsquo;ve been more interested in machine learning and completed some online courses on this broad subject. I&amp;rsquo;m looking forward to learn more while applying these new skills on pet projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please get in touch if there&amp;rsquo;s something I can help with in your current or future projects.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello, my name is Martin</title>
      <link>https://mmartinov.com/page/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Feb 2016 12:46:30 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mmartinov.com/page/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&#34;https://mmartinov.com/post/2015-03-16-climbing-first-attempts/&#34;&gt;first attempts at climbing&lt;/a&gt; were probably around 2001. Since then I&amp;rsquo;ve learned a lot, traveled around, met some awesome people and made many new friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end of March 2015 I had a nasty accident - I&amp;rsquo;ve hit the deck falling from 10 meters and fractured few vertebrae. Fortunately, a great deal of luck was involved and I was able to recover very quickly. Month and a half later I&amp;rsquo;ve spent a week on the rocks of North Wales while taking part in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/mmartinov/sets/72157652624400499&#34;&gt;BMC International Summer Meet&lt;/a&gt; which was an absolutely rad experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Climbing is what makes me feel alive, it fuels my desire to learn and grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this all sounds interesting but you&amp;rsquo;re here to learn about my software development services, you probably want to have a look at my &lt;a href=&#34;https://mmartinov.com/page/work&#34;&gt;professional resume&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>